<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>spiral galaxy on Nights of Wren</title>
    <link>https://astro.wren.dev/tags/spiral-galaxy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in spiral galaxy on Nights of Wren</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://astro.wren.dev/tags/spiral-galaxy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>M 31, The Andromeda Galaxy</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-06-28-m31-andromeda-gal/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-06-28-m31-andromeda-gal/</guid>
      <description>Approximately 245 million lightyears in the direction of the constellation Andromeda, The Andromeda Galaxy (also known as M 31 and NGC 224, formerly the Great Spiral Nebula in Andromeda) is our closest neighboring galaxy of similar size, and is projected to merge with the Milky Way in 4-5 billion years. The Andromeda Galaxy played an important role in The Great Debate concerning the size of the universe and the nature of spiral galaxies &amp;ndash; then called spiral nebulae or island universes, depending on your side of the argument. The debate was settled in 1925 after Edwin Hubble measured the distance to Andromeda using Cepheid variable stars, and determined it was far outside the range of the Milky Way.
Captured over two nights using a Fujifilm X-A5 and a GSO 6&amp;quot; F/4 Newtonian mounted on a Celestron AVX, and processed with Siril and GIMP. This image is a stack of 5.5 hours total integration time distributed over 221 exposures at 1000 ISO, and calibrated using 40 biases, flats, and darks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>M 51, The Whirlpool Galaxy</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-04-15-m51-whirlpool-gal/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-04-15-m51-whirlpool-gal/</guid>
      <description>Discovered in 1773 by Charles Messier, M 51 is a famous pair of interacting galaxies approximately 28 million light-years away from Earth in the direction of the constellation Canes Venatici.[1] The larger M 51a was discovered in 1773 by Charles Messier, and its companion dwarf galaxy M 51b was discovered by his friend Pierre Méchain in 1781. The Whirlpool Galaxy is the first deep-sky object to be described as having a spiral structure, sketched by Lord Rosse in 1845. Debate over the nature of these &amp;ldquo;spiral nebulae&amp;rdquo; would later lead to the discovery that the Milky Way is just one of unthinkably many galaxies in the universe. The Whirlpool Galaxy is home to candidate exoplanet M51-ULS-1b, which would be the first known exoplanet outside our galaxy if confirmed. Initial observations suggest it is a Saturn-sized planet orbiting a binary system of a massive star and either a black hole or neutron star at a distance of about 10 astronomical units.[2]
Captured using a Fujifilm X-A5 and a GSO 6&amp;quot; F/4 Newtonian mounted on a Celestron AVX, with a GSO Coma Corrector and guided with a ZWO ASI120MM Mini and an Svbony SV1665. This image is a stack of 55x90s exposures at 1250 ISO, calibrated with 30 flats, 21 darks, and 50 bias frames. Processed using (1) Siril for pre-processing, stacking, background extraction, and photometric color calibration, and (2) GIMP for wavelet decomposition, sharpening, and final color balance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>M 81, Bode&#39;s Galaxy</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-05-09-m81-bodes-gal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-05-09-m81-bodes-gal/</guid>
      <description>12 million light years away[1], tucked midway between Ursa Major&amp;rsquo;s head and Draco&amp;rsquo;s tail, lies the core of the M 81 galaxy group &amp;ndash; one of the closest neighbors to our Local Group. M 81 and M 82, the largest and brightest of the group, were independently discovered by Johann Elert Bode and Pierre Méchain in 1774 and 1779 respectively, while the less conspicuous NGC 3077 was discovered slightly later by William Herschel in 1801. The gravitational disruptions caused by their close interactions have had effects on each of the three galaxies, but the most drastically effected was M 82.
M 82, also known as The Cigar Galaxy, is a nearly edge-on spiral galaxy[2] distorted by a close encounter with Bode&amp;rsquo;s Galaxy 200-500 million years ago. This channeled a large amount of gas towards the galactic core, which has caused several starbursts, the birth of several generations of new stars at many times the average rate.[3] This rapid star formation ejects large amounts of dust and gas into intergalactic space with a force known as galactic superwind &amp;ndash; a combination of kinetic energy from supernovae and stellar wind from large clusters of newly formed stars.[4] In M 82, the conditions were right for this material to form vast filaments glowing brightly in hydrogen alpha, infrared, and X-ray wavelengths, visible in this Hubble image .
Captured over two nights using a Fujifilm X-A5 and a GSO 6&amp;quot; F/4 Newtonian mounted on a Celestron AVX, and processed with Siril and GIMP. This image is a stack of 5.5 hours total integration time distributed over 221 exposures at 1000 ISO, and calibrated using 40 biases, flats, and darks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>M 101, The Pinwheel Galaxy</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-03-29-m101-pinwheel-gal/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-03-29-m101-pinwheel-gal/</guid>
      <description>The Pinwheel Galaxy is a face-on spiral galaxy found just off the handle of the Big Dipper. It is around 21 million light-years away[1] , and has a diameter of around 170,000 light-years. It is notable for its high concentration of HII regions: clouds of ionized hydrogen gas glowing a deep red due to the same mechanism that makes certain materials glow under a black light. Unfortunately my camera at the time was not very sensitive to the specific wavelength of light generated by these clouds so they appear more white, but the largest and brightest of them are nonetheless annotated.
M 101 was one of only three objects (101-103) which Charles Messier did not personally verify through observation before adding to his ubiquitous catalog, instead relying on the word of his colleague Pierre Méchain, who had discovered about a quarter of the catalog&amp;rsquo;s entries. M 102 in particular was a subject of much controversy, because it was said to be between the stars Omicron Boötis and Iota Draconis &amp;ndash; two stars which would not make much sense to use due to their distance from one another. Two years after the original publication of the catalog, Méchain submitted a retraction letter, stating that M 101 and M 102 &amp;ldquo;are nothing but the same nebula, which has been taken for two, by an error in the charts.&amp;rdquo; Although some ambiguity remains, most modern sources are of the opinion that M 102 is not a duplicate of M 101, arguing that Méchain had intended to write a theta &amp;ldquo;θ&amp;rdquo; and not an omicron &amp;ldquo;ο&amp;rdquo;, which would place NGC 5866 in the correct position to be the missing galaxy.
Captured using a Fujifilm X-A5 and a GSO 6&amp;quot; F/4 Newtonian sans coma corrector mounted on an unguided Celestron AVX. This image is a stack of 43x60s light frames taken at 1600 ISO, calibrated with 30 flats, 20 darks, and 30 biases. Reprocessed on 03/13/23 using (1) Siril for stacking, cropping, RBF background extraction, color calibration, and a generalized hyperbolic stretch, (2) StarNet++ v2 for star removal, after which the starless image got sent through (3) GIMP to patch up some walking noise with the clone stamp, reduce the background noise using the fill tool on a translucent masked layer, and adjust the color balance in the galaxy arms, then back into (4) Siril again to tweak the black point and recombine the star mask with a modified asinh stretch.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
