<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>spiral galaxy on Nights of Wren</title>
    <link>https://astro.wren.dev/tags/spiral-galaxy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in spiral galaxy on Nights of Wren</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://astro.wren.dev/tags/spiral-galaxy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>M 31, The Andromeda Galaxy</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-06-28-m31-andromeda-gal/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-06-28-m31-andromeda-gal/</guid>
      <description>Approximately 245 million lightyears in the direction of the constellation Andromeda, The Andromeda Galaxy (also known as M 31 and NGC 224, formerly the Great Spiral Nebula in Andromeda) is our closest neighboring galaxy of similar size, and is projected to merge with the Milky Way in 4-5 billion years. The Andromeda Galaxy played an important role in The Great Debate concerning the size of the universe and the nature of spiral galaxies &amp;ndash; then called spiral nebulae or island universes, depending on your side of the argument.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>M 51, The Whirlpool Galaxy</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-04-15-m51-whirlpool-gal/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-04-15-m51-whirlpool-gal/</guid>
      <description>Discovered in 1773 by Charles Messier, M 51 is a famous pair of interacting galaxies approximately 28 million light-years away from Earth in the direction of the constellation Canes Venatici.[1] The larger M 51a was discovered in 1773 by Charles Messier, and its companion dwarf galaxy M 51b was discovered by his friend Pierre Méchain in 1781. The Whirlpool Galaxy is the first deep-sky object to be described as having a spiral structure, sketched by Lord Rosse in 1845.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>M 101, The Pinwheel Galaxy</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-03-29-m101-pinwheel-gal/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-03-29-m101-pinwheel-gal/</guid>
      <description>The Pinwheel Galaxy is a face-on spiral galaxy found just off the handle of the Big Dipper. It is around 21 million light-years away[1], and has a diameter of around 170,000 light-years. It is notable for its high concentration of HII regions: clouds of ionized hydrogen gas glowing a deep red due to the same mechanism that makes certain materials glow under a black light. Unfortunately my camera at the time was not very sensitive to the specific wavelength of light generated by these clouds so they appear more white, but the largest and brightest of them are nonetheless annotated.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
