<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gallery on Nights of Wren</title>
    <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Gallery on Nights of Wren</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>M 97, The Owl Nebula</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2023-02-16-m97-owl-neb/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2023-02-16-m97-owl-neb/</guid>
      <description>What to do with a planetary imaging train after the planets are out of sight? My main camera was out of commission, so I had to make due with the setup I was using: a high-magnification lens paired a camera with very small pixels, on an unguided mount that I never bothered to accurately polar align. Not ideal for dimmer targets, but I figured since the camera I was using had low read noise, I could just take a few hundred or thousand short exposures and still get something useful through the noise.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Full Moon Mosaic</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-10-11-moon-mosaic/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-10-11-moon-mosaic/</guid>
      <description>Believe it or not, full moons are generally considered bad news for astrophotographers. Faint details in a target can easily be swamped in the strong glow of the moon, especially when considered in tandem with artificial light pollution, and seasoned lunar photographers tend to prefer the high-contrast view of shadows cast by craters. But, to my good luck, I am not a seasoned lunar photographer, and am just as impressed a full moon as the rest of the world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jupiter in Monochrome</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-08-03-jupiter/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-08-03-jupiter/</guid>
      <description>My first successful attempt at planetary photography! This was a tough job for my equipment, since my telescope is designed to be good at efficiently capturing long exposures of large dim objects like diffuse nebulae and not high-resolution millisecond-scale exposures of small bright objects. That said, I get a kick out of using my equipment wrong, and I&amp;rsquo;m very pleased with the amount of detail that&amp;rsquo;s visible. The Great Red Spot remains impressive even through a monochrome camera depriving it of its signature color.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>M 31, The Andromeda Galaxy</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-06-28-m31-andromeda-gal/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-06-28-m31-andromeda-gal/</guid>
      <description>Approximately 245 million lightyears in the direction of the constellation Andromeda, The Andromeda Galaxy (also known as M 31 and NGC 224, formerly the Great Spiral Nebula in Andromeda) is our closest neighboring galaxy of similar size, and is projected to merge with the Milky Way in 4-5 billion years. The Andromeda Galaxy played an important role in The Great Debate concerning the size of the universe and the nature of spiral galaxies &amp;ndash; then called spiral nebulae or island universes, depending on your side of the argument.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>M 27, The Dumbbell Nebula</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-06-18-m27-dumbbell-neb/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-06-18-m27-dumbbell-neb/</guid>
      <description>The Dumbbell Nebula (also known as M 27, NGC 6853, PK 060-03.1, and The Apple Core Nebula) is a vibrant funeral display of a star estimated to have died around 10,000 years ago. What remains is a white dwarf, surrounded by a glowing cloud of gas that made up its outer layers as a red giant. The Dumbbell Nebula was discovered in 1764, and was the first of its kind to be found.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>C 33, The Eastern Veil Nebula</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-05-30-c33-eastern-veil-neb/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-05-30-c33-eastern-veil-neb/</guid>
      <description>The Eastern Veil Nebula (also known as C 33, NGC 6992, and Ced 182b) is part of a large emissive supernova remnant called the Cygnus Loop. The Cygnus Loop in its entirety is estimated be around 10 to 20 thousand years old, 2670 lightyears away from Earth, and 120 lightyears across. The Eastern Veil is a portion of this larger nebula that emits relatively bright light in visible wavelengths due to high concentrations of oxygen, sulphur, and hydrogen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sh2-142, The Wizard Nebula</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-05-20-sh2-142-wizard-neb/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-05-20-sh2-142-wizard-neb/</guid>
      <description>The Wizard Nebula, also known as Sh2-142 is an emission nebula of mostly hydrogen found approximately 8500 light-years[1] in the direction of the constellation Cepheus. It&amp;rsquo;s commonly assigned the name NGC 7380, however that name more accurately given to the cluster of stars which have been born from the gas. Of this cluster, two stars in close orbit around each other &amp;ndash; collectively named DH Cephei &amp;ndash; are responsible for the surrounding nebula&amp;rsquo;s red glow.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Total Lunar Eclipse</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-05-15-lunar-eclipse/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-05-15-lunar-eclipse/</guid>
      <description>During a lunar eclipse, the moon appears red due to the way the light interacts with Earth&amp;rsquo;s atmosphere. Since the Earth is blocking direct sunlight, the only light it can receive has been refracted through the atmosphere, and the photons most likely to survive the trip are those with longer wavelengths: red light. This phenomenon is called Rayleigh Scattering, and it&amp;rsquo;s also responsible for the color of sunsets and the sky during the day.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>IC 5067, The Pelican Nebula</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-05-10-ic5067-pelican-neb/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-05-10-ic5067-pelican-neb/</guid>
      <description>The smaller next-door neighbor of the North America Nebula, the Pelican Nebula (also known as IC 5067, LBN 353, and Ced 183a) is a hydrogen alpha emission nebula in the constellation Cygnus. Captured using a Fujifilm X-A5 and a GSO 6&amp;quot; F/4 Newtonian mounted on a Celestron AVX, processed with Siril and GIMP. This image is a stack of 3 hours total integration time distributed over 120 exposures at 1000 ISO, and calibrated with 100 biases, 40 flats, and 40 darks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>M 13, Hercules Globular Cluster</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-04-11-m13-hercules-glob/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-04-11-m13-hercules-glob/</guid>
      <description>Discovered in 1714 by Edmond Halley of comet fame, M 13 is one of about 160 known globular clusters orbiting the Milky Way[1] &amp;ndash; dense clusters of upwards of several hundred thousand stars that orbit around a host galaxy. Their origins are not well-understood since most of them are on the order of 10 billion years old, but they may be a halfway step between an open star cluster and a compact galaxy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warmup Moonshot</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-04-11-moon/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-04-11-moon/</guid>
      <description>Back before I had my trusty electronic focuser or the 3D-printed Bahtinov mask I used before that, I used to warm up with some quick pictures of the moon to verify that I was in-focus, and that my telescope mount could find its targets with reasonable accuracy. I&amp;rsquo;ve always been happy with how this one turned out, so I thought I&amp;rsquo;d upload it as a mini behind the scenes.
Captured using a Fujifilm X-A5 and a GSO 6&amp;quot; F/4 Newtonian mounted on an untracked Celestron AVX.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>M 101, The Pinwheel Galaxy</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-03-29-m101-pinwheel-gal/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-03-29-m101-pinwheel-gal/</guid>
      <description>The Pinwheel Galaxy is a face-on spiral galaxy found just off the handle of the Big Dipper. It is around 21 million light-years away[1], and has a diameter of around 170,000 light-years. It is notable for its high concentration of HII regions: clouds of ionized hydrogen gas glowing a deep red due to the same mechanism that makes certain materials glow under a black light. Unfortunately my camera at the time was not very sensitive to the specific wavelength of light generated by these clouds so they appear more white, but the largest and brightest of them are nonetheless annotated.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>M 42, The Orion Nebula</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-03-24-m42-orion-neb/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-03-24-m42-orion-neb/</guid>
      <description>If you were to ask someone on the street what they know about the constellation Orion, they&amp;rsquo;d probably just mention the belt and keep walking. But if that someone happened to be an astronomer, they might be more inclined to start by talking about the Orion complex. The Orion complex is a vast network of interstellar gas and dust spanning the entire constellation, and home to the closest stellar nurseries to Earth.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
