<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>emission-nebula on Nights of Wren</title>
    <link>https://astro.wren.dev/tags/emission-nebula/</link>
    <description>Recent content in emission-nebula on Nights of Wren</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://astro.wren.dev/tags/emission-nebula/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>M 97, The Owl Nebula</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2023-02-16-m97-owl-neb/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2023-02-16-m97-owl-neb/</guid>
      <description>What to do with a planetary imaging train after the planets are out of sight? My main camera was out of commission, so I had to make due with the setup I was using: a high-magnification lens paired a camera with very small pixels, on an unguided mount that I never bothered to accurately polar align. Not ideal for dimmer targets, but I figured since the camera I was using had low read noise, I could just take a few hundred or thousand short exposures and still get something useful through the noise. So I looked up some potential targets, picked M 97, found the nearest bright star with the help of my finder scope, and began hopping over, being careful to confidently identify the location of each frame I took on my way there. When I arrived, I decided to push my luck, since the 5-second exposures I used to find my way over looked very sharp, and managed to push all the way to 60 seconds with most of the frames still coming out looking good, which allowed for the resolution of fainter details.
So what is it? M 97 is a planetary nebula, a glowing cloud of ionized elements which previously made up the outer layers of a recently-dead average-sized star. A planetary nebula is essentially the equivalent of a supernova for stars which don&amp;rsquo;t have enough mass. Although this particular example is rather spherical and symmetrical in shape, planetary nebulae come in a surprisingly wide variety of shapes, with new research suggesting this variation is caused by the same mechanism which shapes its stellar winds in its prior stage of evolution, possibly gravitational interaction with large planets or brown dwarfs in its orbit.[1] M 97 was discovered by Pierre Méchain on February 16, 1781 &amp;ndash; meaning this image was, by sheer coincidence, taken precisely on the 242nd anniversary of its discovery. It is estimated to be about 8000 years old and two to three thousand light years away.
Captured with a ZWO ASI120MM Mini, a Tele-Vue 2x Barlow Lens, a set of Baader LRGB filters, and a GSO 6&amp;quot; F/4 mounted on a Celestron AVX. The luminance frames were stacked using DeepSkyStacker, and most of the remaining processing was in Siril: manually registering (not enough stars visible in the small FOV for automation) and stacking each RGB channel, aligning the channels and compositing them with luminance, RBF background extraction, and a histogram stretch. I ran it through Starnet++, and finished processing in GIMP by throwing some layer masks on a wavelet decomposition, making some tweaks to the saturation, brightness, and contrast, and re-adding the stars. The final image is a stack of 37x60s luminance, 9x60s red, 11x60s green, and 13x60s blue frames, calibrated with 20 dark and 500 bias per binning level, and 20 flat frames per filter. Luminance frames were taken at binning 1, and RGB frames were taken at binning 2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>M 27, The Dumbbell Nebula</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-06-18-m27-dumbbell-neb/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-06-18-m27-dumbbell-neb/</guid>
      <description>The Dumbbell Nebula (also known as M 27, NGC 6853, PK 060-03.1, and The Apple Core Nebula) is a vibrant funeral display of a star estimated to have died around 10,000 years ago. What remains is a white dwarf, surrounded by a glowing cloud of gas that made up its outer layers as a red giant. The Dumbbell Nebula was discovered in 1764, and was the first of its kind to be found. The first observers of this new class of object noted they appeared somewhat similar to a very dim planet through their telescopes, and this is thought to be the source of a misnomer that persists to this day: even though modern astronomers know they have nothing to do with planets, they are still called planetary nebulae.
Captured using a Fujifilm X-A5 and a GSO 6&amp;quot; F/4 Newtonian mounted on a Celestron AVX, and processed with Siril and GIMP. This image is a stack of just under 4 hours total integration time distributed over 155 exposures at 1000 ISO, and calibrated using 40 biases, flats, and darks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>C 33, The Eastern Veil Nebula</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-05-30-c33-eastern-veil-neb/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-05-30-c33-eastern-veil-neb/</guid>
      <description>The Eastern Veil Nebula (also known as C 33, NGC 6992, and Ced 182b) is part of a large emissive supernova remnant called the Cygnus Loop. The Cygnus Loop in its entirety is estimated be around 10 to 20 thousand years old, 2670 lightyears away from Earth, and 120 lightyears across. The Eastern Veil is a portion of this larger nebula that emits relatively bright light in visible wavelengths due to high concentrations of oxygen, sulphur, and hydrogen. It gets its wispy appearance from shock fronts caused by the initial explosion.
Captured over two nights using a Fujifilm X-A5 and a GSO 6&amp;quot; F/4 Newtonian mounted on a Celestron AVX, and processed with Siril and GIMP. This image is a stack of 6.6 hours total integration time distributed over 265 exposures at 1000 ISO. The second night was calibrated with 40 biases, flats, and darks, but the first night only had flats because I forgot do take any biases or darks. I was using a pretty aggressive dither though, so it worked out well enough 🤷</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sh2-142, The Wizard Nebula</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-05-20-sh2-142-wizard-neb/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-05-20-sh2-142-wizard-neb/</guid>
      <description>The Wizard Nebula, also known as Sh2-142 is an emission nebula of mostly hydrogen found approximately 8500 light-years[1] in the direction of the constellation Cepheus. It&amp;rsquo;s commonly assigned the name NGC 7380, however that name more accurately given to the cluster of stars which have been born from the gas. Of this cluster, two stars in close orbit around each other &amp;ndash; collectively named DH Cephei &amp;ndash; are responsible for the surrounding nebula&amp;rsquo;s red glow.[2] The radiation coming from these exceptionally bright young stars kicks some electrons into unstable higher-energy orbits around their nucleus, before they quickly fall back to a lower more stable orbit and eject a photon with a wavelength that making up the difference in energy between the two. (This is the same process that makes fluorescent paint glow under a black light!)
Captured over two nights, the 17th and the 20th, using a Fujifilm X-A5 and a GSO 6&amp;quot; F/4 Newtonian mounted on a Celestron AVX, with a GSO Coma Corrector and guided by a ZWO ASI120MM Mini and an Svbony SV165. The first night was 143x90s exposures at 1250 ISO, calibrated with 60 flats, 40 darks, and 60 bias frames. The second night was 126x90s exposures at 1250 ISO, also calibrated with 60 flats, 40 darks, and 60 bias frames. The two nights were stacked together with Siril, which was also used for background extraction and photometric color calibration. Wavelet decomposition and other final touches were done in GIMP. I definitely did some kind of star reduction on this picture, but I don&amp;rsquo;t think I was using Starnet++ at this time, so I&amp;rsquo;m honestly not sure how I did it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>IC 5067, The Pelican Nebula</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-05-10-ic5067-pelican-neb/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-05-10-ic5067-pelican-neb/</guid>
      <description>The smaller next-door neighbor of the North America Nebula, the Pelican Nebula (also known as IC 5067, LBN 353, and Ced 183a) is a hydrogen alpha emission nebula in the constellation Cygnus. Captured using a Fujifilm X-A5 and a GSO 6&amp;quot; F/4 Newtonian mounted on a Celestron AVX, processed with Siril and GIMP. This image is a stack of 3 hours total integration time distributed over 120 exposures at 1000 ISO, and calibrated with 100 biases, 40 flats, and 40 darks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>M 42, The Orion Nebula</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-03-24-m42-orion-neb/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-03-24-m42-orion-neb/</guid>
      <description>If you were to ask someone on the street what they know about the constellation Orion, they&amp;rsquo;d probably just mention the belt and keep walking. But if that someone happened to be an astronomer, they might be more inclined to start by talking about the Orion complex. The Orion complex is a vast network of interstellar gas and dust spanning the entire constellation, and home to the closest stellar nurseries to Earth. One such stellar nursery is M 42, the photogenic Orion Nebula: by far the brightest nebula in the northern hemisphere, visible to the naked eye even near a city. It can be found in the middle of the asterism Orion&amp;rsquo;s Sword, with its fuzzy appearance distinguishing it from the stars around it. It owes this fuzz to the nebulosity around the Trapezium Cluster, which scatters and reflects the star cluster&amp;rsquo;s light &amp;ndash; mostly coming from the massive binary star 41 Ori C. This same star cluster causes most of the pink glow visible in photos, which is due to hydrogen atoms absorbing and re-emitting light at a specific wavelength of red, and it also helps to illuminate the dimmer parts of the nebula.
Captured using a Fujifilm X-A5 and a GSO 6&amp;quot; F/4 Newtonian mounted on a Celestron AVX, processed with Siril and GIMP. This image is a stack of 38x30s light frames taken at 1600 ISO. This was before I understood the importance of calibration frames, so none were used &amp;ndash; I simply cropped out the worst of the dust motes and vignetting.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
