<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>star-cluster on Nights of Wren</title>
    <link>https://astro.wren.dev/tags/star-cluster/</link>
    <description>Recent content in star-cluster on Nights of Wren</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://astro.wren.dev/tags/star-cluster/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>M 13, Hercules Globular Cluster</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-04-11-m13-hercules-glob/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-04-11-m13-hercules-glob/</guid>
      <description>Discovered in 1714 by Edmond Halley of comet fame, M 13 is one of about 160 known globular clusters orbiting the Milky Way[1] &amp;ndash; dense clusters of upwards of several hundred thousand stars that orbit around a host galaxy. Their origins are not well-understood since most of them are on the order of 10 billion years old, but they may be a halfway step between an open star cluster and a compact galaxy.[2] Because of how tightly-packed their stars are, globular clusters are excellent environments to study certain interactions that are otherwise very rare.
M 13 is noteworthy among globular clusters for being one of the largest and brightest visible in the Northern Hemisphere. It was chosen as the target of the 1974 Arecibo Message : one of the first attempts at interstellar communication with an extraterrestrial intelligence, a short pictographic message with basic information about humanity which will reach the cluster in around 25,000 years. It also contains an interesting star called NGC 6205 Barnard 29 (the blue-fringed star annotated on the left side of the cluster) which is predicted to be in the process of becoming a planetary nebula[3] &amp;ndash; a rare event for astronomers a few thousand years in the future to appreciate!
Captured using a Fujifilm X-A5 and a GSO 6&amp;quot; F/4 Newtonian mounted on an untracked Celestron AVX. I had a coma corrector at this point, but I hadn&amp;rsquo;t yet learned that the proper backspacing changes with focal ratio, I didn&amp;rsquo;t have any decent collimation tools, and my guide camera hadn&amp;rsquo;t yet arrived, so my stars are still shaped pretty wonky when you zoom in on them. (This issue would continue for the remainder of the year.) This image is a stack of 34x60s light fames at 1250 ISO, calibrated with 20 flats, 15 darks, and 20 bias frames. Processed with (1) Siril for pre-processing, stacking, and background extraction, and (2) GIMP for wavelet decomposition and tweaks to color grading.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
