<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>messier-object on Nights of Wren</title>
    <link>https://astro.wren.dev/tags/messier-object/</link>
    <description>Recent content in messier-object on Nights of Wren</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://astro.wren.dev/tags/messier-object/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>M 97, The Owl Nebula</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2023-02-16-m97-owl-neb/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2023-02-16-m97-owl-neb/</guid>
      <description>What to do with a planetary imaging train after the planets are out of sight? My main camera was out of commission, so I had to make due with the setup I was using: a high-magnification lens paired a camera with very small pixels, on an unguided mount that I never bothered to accurately polar align. Not ideal for dimmer targets, but I figured since the camera I was using had low read noise, I could just take a few hundred or thousand short exposures and still get something useful through the noise. So I looked up some potential targets, picked M 97, found the nearest bright star with the help of my finder scope, and began hopping over, being careful to confidently identify the location of each frame I took on my way there. When I arrived, I decided to push my luck, since the 5-second exposures I used to find my way over looked very sharp, and managed to push all the way to 60 seconds with most of the frames still coming out looking good, which allowed for the resolution of fainter details.
So what is it? M 97 is a planetary nebula, a glowing cloud of ionized elements which previously made up the outer layers of a recently-dead average-sized star. A planetary nebula is essentially the equivalent of a supernova for stars which don&amp;rsquo;t have enough mass. Although this particular example is rather spherical and symmetrical in shape, planetary nebulae come in a surprisingly wide variety of shapes, with new research suggesting this variation is caused by the same mechanism which shapes its stellar winds in its prior stage of evolution, possibly gravitational interaction with large planets or brown dwarfs in its orbit.[1] M 97 was discovered by Pierre Méchain on February 16, 1781 &amp;ndash; meaning this image was, by sheer coincidence, taken precisely on the 242nd anniversary of its discovery. It is estimated to be about 8000 years old and two to three thousand light years away.
Captured with a ZWO ASI120MM Mini, a Tele-Vue 2x Barlow Lens, a set of Baader LRGB filters, and a GSO 6&amp;quot; F/4 mounted on a Celestron AVX. The luminance frames were stacked using DeepSkyStacker, and most of the remaining processing was in Siril: manually registering (not enough stars visible in the small FOV for automation) and stacking each RGB channel, aligning the channels and compositing them with luminance, RBF background extraction, and a histogram stretch. I ran it through Starnet++, and finished processing in GIMP by throwing some layer masks on a wavelet decomposition, making some tweaks to the saturation, brightness, and contrast, and re-adding the stars. The final image is a stack of 37x60s luminance, 9x60s red, 11x60s green, and 13x60s blue frames, calibrated with 20 dark and 500 bias per binning level, and 20 flat frames per filter. Luminance frames were taken at binning 1, and RGB frames were taken at binning 2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>M 31, The Andromeda Galaxy</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-06-28-m31-andromeda-gal/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-06-28-m31-andromeda-gal/</guid>
      <description>Approximately 245 million lightyears in the direction of the constellation Andromeda, The Andromeda Galaxy (also known as M 31 and NGC 224, formerly the Great Spiral Nebula in Andromeda) is our closest neighboring galaxy of similar size, and is projected to merge with the Milky Way in 4-5 billion years. The Andromeda Galaxy played an important role in The Great Debate concerning the size of the universe and the nature of spiral galaxies &amp;ndash; then called spiral nebulae or island universes, depending on your side of the argument. The debate was settled in 1925 after Edwin Hubble measured the distance to Andromeda using Cepheid variable stars, and determined it was far outside the range of the Milky Way.
Captured over two nights using a Fujifilm X-A5 and a GSO 6&amp;quot; F/4 Newtonian mounted on a Celestron AVX, and processed with Siril and GIMP. This image is a stack of 5.5 hours total integration time distributed over 221 exposures at 1000 ISO, and calibrated using 40 biases, flats, and darks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>M 27, The Dumbbell Nebula</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-06-18-m27-dumbbell-neb/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-06-18-m27-dumbbell-neb/</guid>
      <description>The Dumbbell Nebula (also known as M 27, NGC 6853, PK 060-03.1, and The Apple Core Nebula) is a vibrant funeral display of a star estimated to have died around 10,000 years ago. What remains is a white dwarf, surrounded by a glowing cloud of gas that made up its outer layers as a red giant. The Dumbbell Nebula was discovered in 1764, and was the first of its kind to be found. The first observers of this new class of object noted they appeared somewhat similar to a very dim planet through their telescopes, and this is thought to be the source of a misnomer that persists to this day: even though modern astronomers know they have nothing to do with planets, they are still called planetary nebulae.
Captured using a Fujifilm X-A5 and a GSO 6&amp;quot; F/4 Newtonian mounted on a Celestron AVX, and processed with Siril and GIMP. This image is a stack of just under 4 hours total integration time distributed over 155 exposures at 1000 ISO, and calibrated using 40 biases, flats, and darks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>M 51, The Whirlpool Galaxy</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-04-15-m51-whirlpool-gal/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-04-15-m51-whirlpool-gal/</guid>
      <description>Discovered in 1773 by Charles Messier, M 51 is a famous pair of interacting galaxies approximately 28 million light-years away from Earth in the direction of the constellation Canes Venatici.[1] The larger M 51a was discovered in 1773 by Charles Messier, and its companion dwarf galaxy M 51b was discovered by his friend Pierre Méchain in 1781. The Whirlpool Galaxy is the first deep-sky object to be described as having a spiral structure, sketched by Lord Rosse in 1845. Debate over the nature of these &amp;ldquo;spiral nebulae&amp;rdquo; would later lead to the discovery that the Milky Way is just one of unthinkably many galaxies in the universe. The Whirlpool Galaxy is home to candidate exoplanet M51-ULS-1b, which would be the first known exoplanet outside our galaxy if confirmed. Initial observations suggest it is a Saturn-sized planet orbiting a binary system of a massive star and either a black hole or neutron star at a distance of about 10 astronomical units.[2]
Captured using a Fujifilm X-A5 and a GSO 6&amp;quot; F/4 Newtonian mounted on a Celestron AVX, with a GSO Coma Corrector and guided with a ZWO ASI120MM Mini and an Svbony SV1665. This image is a stack of 55x90s exposures at 1250 ISO, calibrated with 30 flats, 21 darks, and 50 bias frames. Processed using (1) Siril for pre-processing, stacking, background extraction, and photometric color calibration, and (2) GIMP for wavelet decomposition, sharpening, and final color balance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>M 81, Bode&#39;s Galaxy</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-05-09-m81-bodes-gal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-05-09-m81-bodes-gal/</guid>
      <description>12 million light years away[1], tucked midway between Ursa Major&amp;rsquo;s head and Draco&amp;rsquo;s tail, lies the core of the M 81 galaxy group &amp;ndash; one of the closest neighbors to our Local Group. M 81 and M 82, the largest and brightest of the group, were independently discovered by Johann Elert Bode and Pierre Méchain in 1774 and 1779 respectively, while the less conspicuous NGC 3077 was discovered slightly later by William Herschel in 1801. The gravitational disruptions caused by their close interactions have had effects on each of the three galaxies, but the most drastically effected was M 82.
M 82, also known as The Cigar Galaxy, is a nearly edge-on spiral galaxy[2] distorted by a close encounter with Bode&amp;rsquo;s Galaxy 200-500 million years ago. This channeled a large amount of gas towards the galactic core, which has caused several starbursts, the birth of several generations of new stars at many times the average rate.[3] This rapid star formation ejects large amounts of dust and gas into intergalactic space with a force known as galactic superwind &amp;ndash; a combination of kinetic energy from supernovae and stellar wind from large clusters of newly formed stars.[4] In M 82, the conditions were right for this material to form vast filaments glowing brightly in hydrogen alpha, infrared, and X-ray wavelengths, visible in this Hubble image .
Captured over two nights using a Fujifilm X-A5 and a GSO 6&amp;quot; F/4 Newtonian mounted on a Celestron AVX, and processed with Siril and GIMP. This image is a stack of 5.5 hours total integration time distributed over 221 exposures at 1000 ISO, and calibrated using 40 biases, flats, and darks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>M 13, Hercules Globular Cluster</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-04-11-m13-hercules-glob/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-04-11-m13-hercules-glob/</guid>
      <description>Discovered in 1714 by Edmond Halley of comet fame, M 13 is one of about 160 known globular clusters orbiting the Milky Way[1] &amp;ndash; dense clusters of upwards of several hundred thousand stars that orbit around a host galaxy. Their origins are not well-understood since most of them are on the order of 10 billion years old, but they may be a halfway step between an open star cluster and a compact galaxy.[2] Because of how tightly-packed their stars are, globular clusters are excellent environments to study certain interactions that are otherwise very rare.
M 13 is noteworthy among globular clusters for being one of the largest and brightest visible in the Northern Hemisphere. It was chosen as the target of the 1974 Arecibo Message : one of the first attempts at interstellar communication with an extraterrestrial intelligence, a short pictographic message with basic information about humanity which will reach the cluster in around 25,000 years. It also contains an interesting star called NGC 6205 Barnard 29 (the blue-fringed star annotated on the left side of the cluster) which is predicted to be in the process of becoming a planetary nebula[3] &amp;ndash; a rare event for astronomers a few thousand years in the future to appreciate!
Captured using a Fujifilm X-A5 and a GSO 6&amp;quot; F/4 Newtonian mounted on an untracked Celestron AVX. I had a coma corrector at this point, but I hadn&amp;rsquo;t yet learned that the proper backspacing changes with focal ratio, I didn&amp;rsquo;t have any decent collimation tools, and my guide camera hadn&amp;rsquo;t yet arrived, so my stars are still shaped pretty wonky when you zoom in on them. (This issue would continue for the remainder of the year.) This image is a stack of 34x60s light fames at 1250 ISO, calibrated with 20 flats, 15 darks, and 20 bias frames. Processed with (1) Siril for pre-processing, stacking, and background extraction, and (2) GIMP for wavelet decomposition and tweaks to color grading.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>M 101, The Pinwheel Galaxy</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-03-29-m101-pinwheel-gal/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-03-29-m101-pinwheel-gal/</guid>
      <description>The Pinwheel Galaxy is a face-on spiral galaxy found just off the handle of the Big Dipper. It is around 21 million light-years away[1] , and has a diameter of around 170,000 light-years. It is notable for its high concentration of HII regions: clouds of ionized hydrogen gas glowing a deep red due to the same mechanism that makes certain materials glow under a black light. Unfortunately my camera at the time was not very sensitive to the specific wavelength of light generated by these clouds so they appear more white, but the largest and brightest of them are nonetheless annotated.
M 101 was one of only three objects (101-103) which Charles Messier did not personally verify through observation before adding to his ubiquitous catalog, instead relying on the word of his colleague Pierre Méchain, who had discovered about a quarter of the catalog&amp;rsquo;s entries. M 102 in particular was a subject of much controversy, because it was said to be between the stars Omicron Boötis and Iota Draconis &amp;ndash; two stars which would not make much sense to use due to their distance from one another. Two years after the original publication of the catalog, Méchain submitted a retraction letter, stating that M 101 and M 102 &amp;ldquo;are nothing but the same nebula, which has been taken for two, by an error in the charts.&amp;rdquo; Although some ambiguity remains, most modern sources are of the opinion that M 102 is not a duplicate of M 101, arguing that Méchain had intended to write a theta &amp;ldquo;θ&amp;rdquo; and not an omicron &amp;ldquo;ο&amp;rdquo;, which would place NGC 5866 in the correct position to be the missing galaxy.
Captured using a Fujifilm X-A5 and a GSO 6&amp;quot; F/4 Newtonian sans coma corrector mounted on an unguided Celestron AVX. This image is a stack of 43x60s light frames taken at 1600 ISO, calibrated with 30 flats, 20 darks, and 30 biases. Reprocessed on 03/13/23 using (1) Siril for stacking, cropping, RBF background extraction, color calibration, and a generalized hyperbolic stretch, (2) StarNet++ v2 for star removal, after which the starless image got sent through (3) GIMP to patch up some walking noise with the clone stamp, reduce the background noise using the fill tool on a translucent masked layer, and adjust the color balance in the galaxy arms, then back into (4) Siril again to tweak the black point and recombine the star mask with a modified asinh stretch.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>M 42, The Orion Nebula</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-03-24-m42-orion-neb/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-03-24-m42-orion-neb/</guid>
      <description>If you were to ask someone on the street what they know about the constellation Orion, they&amp;rsquo;d probably just mention the belt and keep walking. But if that someone happened to be an astronomer, they might be more inclined to start by talking about the Orion complex. The Orion complex is a vast network of interstellar gas and dust spanning the entire constellation, and home to the closest stellar nurseries to Earth. One such stellar nursery is M 42, the photogenic Orion Nebula: by far the brightest nebula in the northern hemisphere, visible to the naked eye even near a city. It can be found in the middle of the asterism Orion&amp;rsquo;s Sword, with its fuzzy appearance distinguishing it from the stars around it. It owes this fuzz to the nebulosity around the Trapezium Cluster, which scatters and reflects the star cluster&amp;rsquo;s light &amp;ndash; mostly coming from the massive binary star 41 Ori C. This same star cluster causes most of the pink glow visible in photos, which is due to hydrogen atoms absorbing and re-emitting light at a specific wavelength of red, and it also helps to illuminate the dimmer parts of the nebula.
Captured using a Fujifilm X-A5 and a GSO 6&amp;quot; F/4 Newtonian mounted on a Celestron AVX, processed with Siril and GIMP. This image is a stack of 38x30s light frames taken at 1600 ISO. This was before I understood the importance of calibration frames, so none were used &amp;ndash; I simply cropped out the worst of the dust motes and vignetting.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
