<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>deep-sky on Nights of Wren</title>
    <link>https://astro.wren.dev/tags/deep-sky/</link>
    <description>Recent content in deep-sky on Nights of Wren</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://astro.wren.dev/tags/deep-sky/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>M 27, The Dumbbell Nebula</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-06-18-dumbbell-neb/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-06-18-dumbbell-neb/</guid>
      <description>The Dumbbell Nebula (also known as M 27, NGC 6853, PK 060-03.1, and The Apple Core Nebula) is a vibrant funeral display of a star estimated to have died around 10,000 years ago. What remains is a white dwarf, surrounded by a glowing cloud of gas that made up its outer layers as a red giant. The Dumbbell Nebula was discovered in 1764, and was the first of its kind to be found.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>C 33, The Eastern Veil Nebula</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-05-30-c33-eastern-veil-neb/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-05-30-c33-eastern-veil-neb/</guid>
      <description>The Eastern Veil Nebula (also known as C 33, NGC 6992, and Ced 182b) is part of a large emissive supernova remnant called the Cygnus Loop. The Cygnus Loop in its entirety is estimated be around 10 to 20 thousand years old, 2670 lightyears away from Earth, and 120 lightyears across. The Eastern Veil is a portion of this larger nebula that emits relatively bright light in visible wavelengths due to high concentrations of oxygen, sulphur, and hydrogen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>IC 5067, The Pelican Nebula</title>
      <link>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-05-10-ic5067-pelican-neb/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://astro.wren.dev/gallery/2022-05-10-ic5067-pelican-neb/</guid>
      <description>The smaller next-door neighbor of the North America Nebula, the Pelican Nebula (also known as IC 5067, LBN 353, and Ced 183a) is a hydrogen alpha emission nebula in the constellation Cygnus. Captured using a Fujifilm X-A5 and a GSO 6&amp;quot; F/4 mounted on a Celestron AVX, processed with Siril and GIMP. This image is a stack of 3 hours total integration time distributed over 120 exposures at 1000 ISO, and calibrated with 100 biases, 40 flats, and 40 darks.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
